Namishiro
na
mi
shi
ro
（阿良々木(あららぎ)）
今日は全国的に母の日だった
Today, nationwide, is Mother's Day.
Park
p
a
rk
A
Restroom
お母さんが好きな人でも
嫌いな人でも
Regardless of whether or not you like your mother...
Regardless of whether or not your relationship with her is good...
お母さんと仲がいい人でも
仲が悪い人でも
If you're a Japanese citizen, you'll take this matter seriously.
日本国民ならば誰もが
平等に享受することになる母の日
I didn't come to this park with a solid reason.
僕は確固たる目的があって
この公園に来たわけではない
Everyone, please park your bicycles.
Park Management
A
Namishiro Park
Usage Guide
Bicycle Parking
Only purely, randomly, aimlessly...
ただ単に でたらめに
気分 気ままに
Bicycle Parking
A
Cyclocomputer
Saginomiya Heavy  Industries
riding on my mountain bike.
足の向くままに
マウンテンバイクで駆けていたら
Riding and riding until I reached this park.
この公園に
行き着いてしまったのだ
But for me to be the only one in the park even though it's a Sunday...
しかし 日曜日の公園に
僕しかいないだなんて まるで
It's as if I'm the only one in the entire world, isn't it?
世界に僕一人しか
いないみたいじゃないか
This may be a bit of an exaggeration,
というのは いくらなんでも
大げさだとしても
but it feels as if I have the rights to the entire park.
まるで この公園の所有権が
僕に あるかのようだった
もう二度と家には
帰らなくていいみたいな
Like I never need to go back home anymore.
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
That's how I feel right now.
そんな気分になった
I'm just
僕だけ
Only me.
I'm just
alone.
１人だけだから
I'm all alone.
Alone again, huh?
This comes as no surprise.
That's why...
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Koyomi, that's why...!
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Ahh.
また １人か
The dark feelings roll forward
as if they were waves.
そんなことを思った
The dark feelings roll forward
as if they were waves.
When I was looking up the sky,
I was pretty calm,
but now I’ve come to hate my pettiness.
（火憐(かれん)）
そんなことだから
but now I’ve come to hate my pettiness.
Maybe this is what
you call self-loathing?
Normally, I'm not the type to be troubled so easily,
the word “troubles” doesn't have any power over me at all.
兄ちゃんは
そんなことだから…
Normally, I'm not the type to be troubled so easily,
the word “troubles” doesn't have any power over me at all.
But every so often, yes, on such
eventful days as March the 14th
I somehow usually end up in this condition.
Special circumstances,
a unique setting.
I'm very sensitive to such things.
I lose my cool.
And I get restless.
Ahh, normal days
are the best.
Please make tomorrow come sooner...
It's only thanks
to this subtle condition
（阿良々木）はあ…
It's only thanks
to this subtle condition
Salt
Oven
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
that the episode with the snail had started.
Looking at it the other way round,
perhaps the episode wouldn't have had a
beginning if I weren't in that condition.
Typeface used for images: HGP mincho B
Mayoi Snail, Part One
Episode 3
My, my. What do we have here?
（戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)）
あらあら これは これは
I thought the carcass of some dog had been left here...
犬の死体が捨てられていると
思ったら
なんだ 阿良々木くんじゃないの
But what's this? It's Araragi-kun?
What? It was just a greeting.
（戦場ヶ原）
何よ ただの あいさつじゃない
冗談よ
It was only a joke.
Ah, i-it's nothing.
（阿良々木）あっ い… いや
Or perhaps the innocent Araragi-kun was fascinated by my charming clothes...
（戦場ヶ原）
それとも 何
うぶな阿良々木くんは
私のチャーミングな私服姿に
見蕩(みと)れちゃって
plain clothes
supreme bliss
and felt a moment of bliss.
至福の瞬間ということ？
Let's not worry about that pun.
（阿良々木）
そのダジャレは ともかく
確かに見蕩れてしまった
I am indeed fascinated.
But you know, "fascination" is a pretty amazing word, isn't it?
（戦場ヶ原）
それにしても見蕩れるの
“蕩れる”って すごい言葉よね
Did you know...?
知ってる？ 草冠に湯って
書くのよ
Fascination
Animation Number 77C
It's written with a "grass" radical on top of "hot water."
In my heart,
私のなかでは草冠に明るいの
萌えの更に一段上をいく
it's a level above the word "moe," which is written with a "grass" radical on top of "bright."
Moe
Animation Number 77F
People are expecting it to carry onto the next generation.
次世代を担う
センシティブな言葉として
期待が集まっているわ
next world
Note: The Kanji read "Next World" which is a pun for "Maid"
メイド蕩れ とか
Like "maid fascination" or "cat ears fascination."
Cat Ears
猫耳蕩れ とか
They'll be going and saying things like that.
そんなこと言っちゃったりして
ゴホン 前に見た私服とは
随分 印象が違ったから
The impression that these clothes give off
is quite different from the ones I've seen you in before, so I was surprised.
びっくりしたんだよ
それだけだ
That's all.
That's true.
（戦場ヶ原）
ああ それはそうね
That's because I chose to wear more docile clothing at that time.
あのときは おとなしめの服を
ということだったからね
Oh, is that it?
そうなのか？ ふ〜ん
Even so, I bought this set of clothing, top and bottom, yesterday.
（戦場ヶ原）
とはいえ この服は上下ともに昨日
買ったところなのだけれどね
I must say, I'm content.
でも よかったわ
できれば一番最初に
If possible, I wanted you to see it first.
阿良々木くんに
見てほしかったから
ふ〜ん
That you wanted to show it to me first... How do I put it...?
まあ 一番最初に
僕に見せたかったっていうのは
まあ なんつうか
冥利(みょうり)に尽きるというか
Maybe I'm beyond lucky...
I feel honored.
光栄な話だね
I didn't want to show them to you, Araragi-kun.
“見せたかった”じゃないわ
阿良々木くん
I wanted you to see them.
見てほしかったのよ
The nuance in those statements is entirely different.
それとこれとじゃ
ニュアンスが全然 違うじゃない
へえ…
By the way, Araragi-kun...
ところで 阿良々木くん
What are you doing here alone?
こんな所で一体全体
何をしているの？
Well, I was just riding around a bit.
まあ ちょっとしたツーリングだよ
I was riding my bike randomly,
適当に自転車 走らせていたら
ちょっと公園があったんで
and there was a park,
so I decided to stop and rest a bit.
何となく休んでいただけだよ
You?
戦場ヶ原は？ この辺りには
よく来るのか？
Do you come around here often?
This area used to be my turf.
（戦場ヶ原）
この辺りは昔
私の縄張りだったのよ
A
Namishiro Park
Usage Guide
1. There are no trash bins. Take your trash home with you.
2. No dogs allowed in the park.
3. The use of cigarettes and fire is prohibited.
4. Let's take good care of the trees, flowers, and playground equipment.
Your turf...?
（阿良々木）縄張りって…
You mean you used to live around here?
ああ 昔 この辺りに
住んでいたってこと？
Yeah, you could say that.
（戦場ヶ原）まあ そういうこと
Bicycle Parking
But it has changed completely.
でも すっかり変わっちゃった
I'm not going to get sentimental over it,
別に そんなことで
センチメンタルな
気持ちになったりは しないけれど
but the place where I used to live changing is...
でも 自分が昔 住んでいた場所が
変わっていくというのは
It feels like it just cuts off my motivation, for some reason.
どことなくモチベーションが
そがれる感じがするわね
Isn't that inevitable?
しかたないことじゃ ないのか？
You're right. It is inevitable.
そうね　しかたのないことだわ
Hey, Araragi-kun, do you mind if I sit beside you?
ねえ 阿良々木くん
隣 構わないかしら？
（阿良々木）隣？
Beside me?
There's something I want to talk to you about.
あなたと お話がしたいわ
Sure.
（阿良々木）
いいよ　ベンチを１人で
独占していることに
I was starting to feel bad, keeping the entire bench to myself.
若干の心苦しさを
感じていたところだったんだ
Is that so?
（戦場ヶ原）
そう　では 遠慮なく
Then I shall help myself.
（阿良々木）あ…
crab
Animation Number 124
touch
Animation Number 126
About what happened before...
（戦場ヶ原）
この間のこと 改めてお礼を
言わせてもらおうと思って
I wanted to thank you one more time...
You don't need to thank me or anything.
（阿良々木）
ああ いや お礼だなんて
そんなの別に いいよ
You should thank Oshino instead. I think that's more than enough.
礼は忍野(おしの)に言っとけよ
それだけで いいと思うぜ
Well, I have to pay Oshino-san, so it's a bit different.
（戦場ヶ原）
忍野さんには料金を支払うことに
なっているしね
As for you, I wish to express my gratitude differently.
私は阿良々木くんには忍野さんとは
違う意味で お礼を言いたいの
Well, if you are feeling grateful to me...
いや まあ
僕に対して恩を感じるとか
You should just stop now.
そういうのは やめにしとこうぜ
これから仲良くやっていきにくく
なるだろ
Otherwise it will be hard for us to get along from now on.
仲良く… ね
Get along?
Araragi-kun...
阿良々木くん
May I think of you as someone close to me?
私は阿良々木くんのこと
親しく思ってもいいのかしら？
That... Of course.
そりゃ もちろん
But you are the type who doesn't make many friends, right?
でも 阿良々木くんって
あまり友だちを
作るタイプの人間ではないわよね
That was true until last year.
去年までは そうだったよ
Then a paradigm shift occurred during spring break.
ただ 春休みに ちょっとした
パラダイムシフトがあったわけで
spring vacation
Animation Number 151B
Animation Number 151C
What about you?
そういう戦場ヶ原は？
I was the same until recently.
私は ついこの間までよ
More specifically, until I met you.
もっと言うなら阿良々木くんに
出会うまで
What does she mean?
（阿良々木）
何だ こいつ？
And what is this weird situation?
ていうか 何だ？ この状況
It feels as if she's about to confess to me.
まるで これから
告白されてしまいそうな
このシチュエーション
ゴクッ
Which means, Araragi-kun...
つまりね 阿良々木くん
Regardless of what you say, I still wish to reward you for your help.
阿良々木くんが何と言おうと
私は あなたに
お返しがしたいと思うの
After that, we will, for the first time...
それが終わって初めて私たちは
become friends of equal status.
対等な友達同士に
なれると思うの
（阿良々木）あっ あ…
Friends...
友達？
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Friends...
友達…
Back to the main story.
Hence, Araragi-kun, is there anything you want me to do for you?
（戦場ヶ原）
そういう訳で阿良々木くん
Back to the main story.
何か私にしてほしいことは
ないかしら？
Back to the main story.
I will only take one request, but it can be anything.
１つだけ 何でも言うことを
聞いてあげるわ
A-Anything?
（阿良々木）なっ 何でも？
Really, anything is acceptable.
（戦場ヶ原）
本当に何でもいいわよ
No matter what the wish, I will grant it. However, you are limited to only one.
どんな願いでも１つだけ
かなえてあげる
Be it "world domination," "immortality,"
世界征服でも永遠の命でも
"defeating the Saiyans headed to Earth right now"; all is acceptable.
これから地球にやって来る
サイヤ人を倒してほしいでも
（阿良々木）
お前は神龍(シェンロン)をも超える力を
You... Do you possess powers that surpass those of the Eternal Dragon?!
持っているというのか？
当たり前よ
Of course.
Such confidence.
（阿良々木）
肯定しやがった
But indeed, truthfully, I'd prefer to hear a more personal wish.
（戦場ヶ原）
でも まあ 確かに
私としては もっと個人的な
お願いのほうが
助かるのは事実ね
お手軽だもの
Because it's easier.
（阿良々木）だろうな
I'd assume so.
（戦場ヶ原）
本当に何でもいいわよ
Really, anything you want.
For example, you might want me to put a "nyu" at the end of every sentence for a week.
１週間 語尾に“にゅ”と付けて
会話してほしいとか
Or perhaps you will want me to go to class without wearing panties for a week.
１週間 下着を着用せずに
授業を受けてほしいとか
（阿良々木）ああ…
Maybe you'll want me to wake you up every day for a week, wearing nothing but an apron.
（戦場ヶ原）
１週間 毎朝 裸エプロンで
起こしに来てほしいとか
Or you might want me to join you on an enema diet for a week.
１週間 かん腸ダイエットに
つきあってほしいとか
You have many different preferences, don't you?
阿良々木くんにも いろいろ
好みは あるでしょう
You...
（阿良々木）お前…
Do you really think that I'm at that level of maniac perversion?!
僕を そんなレベルのマニアックな
変態だと思ってたのか？
Even coming from you, isn't that way too rude?!
いくら何でも
失礼すぎるだろうが！
No... That... I'm really sorry.
いえ あの 申し訳ないけれど
さすがに そういうのを
I guess if you said you wanted me to do that forever, I wouldn't be able to take it...
一生とか言われると
ちょっと私としては
ついていけないというか
No. Wrong. That's completely wrong!
（阿良々木）
いや 違う 違う 違う！
I'm not angry over the fact that my level of perversion has been lowered.
自分のマニア度を不当に低く
評価されていることに対して
怒ったわけじゃない！
（戦場ヶ原）あら そう
Oh, is that so?
As a reference, I personally recommend "waking you up every day for a week, wearing nothing but an apron."
参考までに
私の個人的な お薦めは
毎朝 裸エプロンで起こす
かしらね
I can also make breakfast for you, if you like.
なんなら ついでに
朝食を作ってあげても いいのよ
Isn't viewing that from behind romantic for a man?
それを後ろから眺めるなんて
なかなか男のロマンじゃない？
You know, Senjougahara...
あのね 戦場ヶ原
Even if we make that sort of arrangement, I think us just being "friends" will be impossible.
仮に そのような交渉が
成立してしまったら
僕たちの間に その後の友情は
ありえなくなると思うんだよ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（戦場ヶ原）あら
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Ah, if you put it that way, you have a point. You're right.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
言われてみれば確かにそうね
そうだったわ
Then let's just say that erotic things are off-limits.
では エロ方面は
禁止ということで
Besides, I figured that you wouldn't ever ask for anything erotic, anyway.
でも どうせ阿良々木くんは
エロ方面の要求なんて
してこないだろうとは
思っていたけれどね
You have a great deal of trust in me.
（阿良々木）
おお えらく信頼されてんじゃん
Well, of course. You're a virgin.
童貞だもの
I guess we did talk about that, didn't we?
（阿良々木）
そんな話も しましたね
Virgins aren't that greedy, so I'm more at ease.
童貞は がっついてないから
相手が楽で いいわ
（阿良々木）あの 戦場ヶ原
Umm... Senjougahara.
お前だって別に経験が
あるわけじゃ ないんだろう？
You don't have any experience either, right?
What are you talking about? Of course I have experience.
何 言ってるの？ 私は経験者よ
そうなのか？
I see...
やりまくりよ
Experience with orgies.
（阿良々木）ウ… ウウン
Say, even if that's true...
えっとな 仮に
本当に そうだったとして
What do you get out of telling me the truth?
その事実を僕に対して
告げることが 戦場ヶ原
お前にとって
何か利益になるのか？
I understand. Correction:
わかったわ　訂正します
I don't have any experience.
経験は ありません　処女です
I'm a virgin.
Huh?
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（戦場ヶ原）
つまり 阿良々木くんみたいな
Which means the only girls who would talk to hopeless virgins like you are
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
いかさない童貞野郎と
話してくれる女の子なんて
at best, late-blooming virgins with mental health issues such as myself.
せいぜい私のような行き遅れの
メンヘル処女しか
いないということよ！
Advertisement Underneath
The conversation seems to have gone a bit astray...
話がそれたけど実際のところ
何かないのかしら？ 阿良々木くん
But honestly, is there anything you need help with, Araragi-kun?
Something that you're just troubled about?
もっと単純に困っていることとか
Troubled...?
（阿良々木）困っていることね…
I'm not a very good talker, so I can't say it very well,
（戦場ヶ原）
私 口下手だから
うまく言えないけれど
but my intention of wanting to help you is sincere.
阿良々木くんの力になりたいと
思っているのは本当なのよ
I see.
（阿良々木）
そうだな あえて言うなら…
If I dare to tell you...
Oh, what is it?
（戦場ヶ原）あら 何かあるの？
Try telling me about it.
話してみてよ　話すだけでも
楽になるものらしいわよ
You'll feel better if you just talk about it. Or so they say, anyway.
Umm...
（阿良々木）えっと…
Lamenting Koyomi
I had a fight with my little sister.
妹とケンカした
Lamenting Koyomi
Seems like something I can't help with very well.
いまいち 力になれそうもない話ね
（阿良々木）がっ！
But for the time being, go ahead and tell me the rest of the story.
（戦場ヶ原）
でも一応 最後まで聞かせて
"For the time being"?
（阿良々木）一応… かよ
Which of your younger sisters did you have a fight with?
（戦場ヶ原）
で どちらの妹さんと
ケンカしたの？
You have two younger sisters, after all, don't you?
確か 阿良々木くん
２人 妹さん いたはずよね
Yeah. You knew that?
（阿良々木）
ああ 知ってるんだっけ
If I had to pick just one, it was the elder one.
どちらかっていうと上のほう
But, really, it was with both of them.
だけど まあ 両方みたいなもんだ
Both of them, always, whatever they do, and wherever they are, stick firmly together.
あいつら何するにしても
いつでも どこでも５Ｗ１Ｈ
完璧に べったりと
つるんでるからな
They are the Tsuganoki Middle School Fire Sisters, after all.
栂(つが)の木(き)二中の
ファイヤーシスターズだものね
You even know their nicknames?
通り名まで知ってんのかよ
Today is Mother's Day, right?
ほら 今日って母の日じゃん
ん？ ああ そういえば
そうだったわね
Now that you mention it, it is, isn't it?
Both of them are really close to our mother.
（阿良々木）
あいつら２人とも
母親に べったりでさ
My mother dotes on them like they're cats.
で 母親のほうも そんな２人を
猫っかわいがりしてるわけよ　で…
And...
なるほど
I see.
As the irresponsible eldest son,
出来の悪い長男としては
母の日である今日 本日 この日
now, on this day, today, Mother's Day, you have no place at home, is that it?
自分の家には
居場所がないというわけね
That's basically it.
（阿良々木）そういうことだ
I tried to sneak out of the house early in the morning, but...
朝早いうちに家をこっそり
抜け出そうとしたんだが
A
Koyomi
Just as I'd gotten on my mountain bike, my sister caught me.
A
Koyomi
マウンテンバイクに乗ったところで
妹に捕まったんだ
A
Koyomi
O
Ka
A
Koyomi
O
Ka
We then had a quarrel.
で 口論
A quarrel?
（戦場ヶ原）口論
O
Ka
My sister wanted me to celebrate Mother's Day together with my mother.
O
Ka
（阿良々木）
妹としては僕にも一緒に母の日を
祝ってほしかったらしいんだが
O
Ka
A
Koyomi
O
Ka
A
Koyomi
But, how do I put it...?
A
Koyomi
何ていうか ほら
僕は そんなの無理だから
A
Koyomi
O
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
You know, I just can't.
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
A
O
Koyomi
Ka
O
Angry Karen
Koyomi, that's why...!
（火憐）
兄ちゃんは そんなことだから
Angry Karen
That's why no matter how much time passes...
そんなことだから
いつまでたっても…
Angry Karen
To sum it all up, a person like me who can't celebrate just one Mother's Day...
（阿良々木）
つまりだ 母の日ひとつ
祝ってやれない自分とか
is angry with himself over what his four-years-younger sister said to him.
４つも年下の妹から言われた言葉に
本気で腹を立てている自分とか
How do I put it...?
そういう 何ていうか
自分の人間の小ささみたいなのが
I'm angry with myself for being such a petty human being.
腹立たしくて 腹立たしくて
しょうがないんだよ
That's a pretty complicated problem.
（戦場ヶ原）
ふ〜ん 複雑な悩みね
It's not complicated. It's just minor.
（阿良々木）
複雑じゃなくて
矮小(わいしょう)なだけなんだよ
"I'm just a really petty person," or something like that.
僕って人間 小さいよな… とか
But even so, the more I think about having to apologize to my sister, the more I don't want to go home.
でも それでも妹に
謝らなきゃならないことを思うと
めちゃくちゃ
家に帰りたくないんだ
You don't want to go home, huh?
（戦場ヶ原）
家に帰りたくない… か
ハア… 残念ながら
あなたの人間の小ささを
I'm afraid to say that in regard to your pettiness, there's nothing I can do, even with my abilities.
私の器量で どうこうすることは
できないわね
How about a little encouragement?
（阿良々木）
努力くらいしてくれよ
It's rather obvious, but in regard to your pettiness, there's nothing I can do, even with my abilities.
（戦場ヶ原）
当然ながら
あなたの人間の小ささを
私の器量で どうこうすることは
できないわね
（阿良々木）ちぇ…
You must be thinking that I'm a boring person...
つまらない人間だよなって
Troubled over such a small thing...
僕の悩みは こんなにちっちゃい
I can't really...
それが嫌だ
stand it.
Small.
（戦場ヶ原）ちっちゃい
It can also be said to be lame. The sort of lameness that comes from getting a fortune told by a fortune teller.
（阿良々木）
しょぼいと言っても いいかな
なんか こう おみくじで
小吉ばっかり引くみたいな
そういう しょぼさ
You can't deny that you're charming, Araragi-kun.
（戦場ヶ原）
自分の魅力を否定してはいけないわ
阿良々木くん
Charming?!
魅力？ 僕の魅力は おみくじで
小吉ばっかり引くことだったのか？
Could it be that my charm has been drawing low-luck from fortune-telling all this time?!
I was kidding.
冗談よ　それに阿良々木くんの
しょぼさは
Besides, your lameness isn't drawing low-luck from fortune-telling.
おみくじで小吉ばっかり
引くみたいなんかじゃないわ
Small
Luck
Photograph
Fortune
Are you trying to say that I'll only be able to draw terrible-luck?
大凶ばっかり引くって
言いたいのか？
Of course not.
まさか それは すごいことじゃない
ていうか おいしいことじゃない
That would be most incredible.
Or rather, that would be quite favorable.
Your lameness is something like...
阿良々木くんの
しょぼさというのはね…
A
The Number 18 Great Fortune
Suginami  Tenmangu Shrine
Poetry Fortune
Continued
Drawing a great-fortune, but when you read it specifically, it doesn't say that anything that good will happen.
（戦場ヶ原）
大吉を引き当てはしたものの
よく読むと
A
Continued
Fortune... 42 points
Life has its ups and downs.
Those who have good fortune
work hard to complete something in their hearts.
Wait through the hard times, and you will
have happiness later.
Continued
内容的には そんな いいことも
書いていないみたいな
A
Continued
Special People...  36 points
Good things come to those who wait.
Patience brings fortune. If you try to hurry it,
you won't see it at all, and your heart will
naturally be dark and lost. Be steadfast and wait.
Continued
A
Health... 28 points
A long sickness is harmful to life,
even when ruined by darkness that came
from evil, it's important to not let it dwell,
the moon is still there when covered
by clouds, you just cannot see its light.
Continued
A
Life... 51 points
You won't be as happy as you think
in the beginning,  after don't hurry to build
your house. If you do so, it will be granted.
The cocoon of happiness will unwrap,
and you will have nothing to worry about.
Continued
A
The Number 18 Great Fortune
Suginami  Tenmangu Shrine
Poetry Fortune
Fortune... 42 points
Life has its ups and downs.
Those who have good fortune
work hard to complete something in their hearts.
Wait through the hard times, and you will
have happiness later.
Special People... 36 points
Good things come to those who wait.
Patience brings fortune. If you try to hurry it,
you won't see it at all, and your heart will
naturally be dark and lost. Be steadfast and wait.
Health... 28 points
A long sickness is harmful to life,
even when ruined by darkness that came
from evil, it's important to not let it dwell,
the moon is still there when covered
by clouds, you just cannot see its light.
Life... 51 points
You won't be as happy as you think
in the beginning,  after don't hurry to build
your house. If you do so, it will be granted.
The cocoon of happiness will unwrap,
and you will have nothing to worry about.
total:157 points (including 400 points)
That sort of lameness.
そういう しょぼさなのよ
That really is lame.
（阿良々木）しょぼ〜！
But Araragi-kun, you look like the type to dote on your sisters.
でも 阿良々木くん 妹なんか
かわいがってそうな ものだけれど
Always quarreling.
（阿良々木）
ケンカばっかりだよ ヘヘッ
Are they ugly sisters who'd make your eyes bleed from looking at them?
目に入れても かわいくない
痛い妹なのね
They don't make my eyes bleed!
（阿良々木）
僕の妹は別に痛くはねえよ
Or did she betray your love?
それとも 愛情の裏返しって
やつなのかしら
Could you secretly be a siscon?
案外 阿良々木くん
シスコンだったりして
No, that's not it.
（阿良々木）違うよ
Falling in love with your sister... is just a fantasy by those who don't have sisters.
妹好きなんてのは
実際に妹のいないヤツの幻想だろ
Okay, then Araragi-kun, you aren't a siscon.
そう 阿良々木くんは
シスコンではないと
You won't fall in love with your sister?
実の妹を
好きになったりはしないと…
How could I?
するか
That's right. You seem more like a sorocon.
そうよね 阿良々木くん
ソロコンぽいもの
Sorocon?
ソロコン？
The short form of sororate marriage. Also known as inter-marriage inclusive of all sisters.
ソロレート婚の略よ
姉妹逆縁婚といって
奥さんが死んだあと
It means marrying the older or younger sister of one's wife who passed away.
奥さんの姉だったり妹だったりと
結婚することを言うの
（阿良々木）う…
Why am I a sorocon?
どうして僕が その
ソロレートとやらに なるんだ？
In your case, Araragi-kun, you will most likely marry the younger sister instead of the older one.
阿良々木くんの場合は
姉ではなく妹ね
Basically, you'll get your wife's younger sister...
つまり 奥さんの妹さんに まずは
“お義兄(にい)ちゃん”と呼ばせておいて
Sororate Marriage Explanation
to call you "Big Brother," and then you'll marry her afterward.
Brother
Mother
Father
Younger Sister
Wife
Karen
Tsukihi
Koyomi
そのあと その子と結婚
Even after getting married, you will still let her call you "Big Brother."
Father
Mother
Death
Younger
Sister
Koyomi
夫婦になっても お義兄ちゃんと
呼ばせ続ける
This is what it originally meant.
これぞ 本当 本来の意味での
現実的な…
Then I definitely killed that previous wife!
Hunt
（阿良々木）
僕 絶対 最初の奥さん
殺してるじゃん！
Well, Araragi-kun, the sorocon...
（戦場ヶ原）
で ソロコンの阿良々木くん
Please call me a siscon. I beg you!
（阿良々木）
シスコンと呼んでください
お願いします！
Didn't you say that you won't fall in love with your sister?
（戦場ヶ原）
実の妹を好きになったりしないと
言うから
I will also not fall in love with the sister of my wife!
（阿良々木）
義理の妹を
好きになったりもしない！
Then will you fall in love with a lover that is not blood-related?
（戦場ヶ原）では 義理の恋人を
（戦場ヶ原）好きになるのかしら？
（阿良々木）だから！
Like I said...!
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Huh? A lover that is not blood-related?
え？ 義理で恋人ができるのか？
フフッ 本当に小さいわね
この程度の軽口で おたおたと
"You sure are petty." Such a small joke is enough to leave you speechless.
Your words are not some small joke, you know.
軽くないじゃん お前の言葉
I was testing you just now.
（戦場ヶ原）
今のは あなたを試したのよ
Why am I being tested?
なんで僕 試されてるの？
Wait, does that mean you're still not going at me at full force?!
ていうか お前 それってまだ
本気を出していないって
ことなのか？
To use my full potential, I'd have to transform.
本気を出すと変身するわよ
Transform?!
変身？ うわ！ すげえ見たい
Wow, I really want to see that!
ハア〜 そういうリアクションは
大きいのに人間は小さいのね
You make such huge reactions, but you yourself are petty.
But regardless of how petty you are, I will never abandon you.
でも 阿良々木くんが
どんなに小さい人間でも
私は見捨てたりはしないの
I will cope with you and your pettiness to the bitter end.
阿良々木くんの人間の小ささに
ちゃんと つきあってあげる
Your words are complicated.
微妙な物言いだよな それも
That's why, besides your pettiness, are there any other things you are troubled about?
（戦場ヶ原）
だから 阿良々木くんの
人間の小ささに関わること以外で
何か困ったことは ない？
How do you plan on scolding me this time?
（阿良々木）
今度は どんな罵倒が
僕に浴びせられるのかな
Your significance has increased. Incredible.
（戦場ヶ原）
器が大きくてステキだわ
Don't praise me in such a forced way!
（阿良々木）
無理やり褒めてんじゃねえ！
Is there really nothing else you wish for?
（戦場ヶ原）本当に何もないの？
Would you like me to help you with your studies?
勉強を教えてほしいとか
I have already given up on that.
（阿良々木）
それは もう諦めてる
卒業できればいい
It's fine as long as I'm able to graduate.
Then do you want me to help you with that?
（戦場ヶ原）じゃ 卒業したいとか
I can live normally and graduate!
（阿良々木）
普通にしてりゃ できるよ！
Then do you want to be normal?
（戦場ヶ原）
じゃあ 普通にしたいとか
Are you picking a fight with me? You are, aren't you?!
ケンカ売ってんだな
そうなんだな？
I guess I am.
じゃあ そうね
Do you want a girlfriend?
（戦場ヶ原）彼女が欲しいとか
（阿良々木）え…
What happens if I say I do?
欲しいって言ったら…
どうなるんだ？
Then you will have a girlfriend. That's all.
彼女が できるわ
それだけのことよ
No, actually I don't really want a girlfriend.
（阿良々木）
いや そういうのは別に ないな
Oh, is that so?
ふ〜ん そう
Buy me some juice next time.
まあ 今度ジュースでも
おごってくれよ
That should settle it.
それでチャラってことに しようぜ
Is that so? That's really unselfish.
そう 無欲なのね
本当に器が大きいわ
You're so noble.
That child was also here just now.
あの子 さっきもいたな
Name
Hey, Senjougahara.
なあ おい 戦場ヶ原
How do you read the name on the name tag of that elementary school kid's bag?
あの小学生のリュックサックの名札
あれ 何て読むんだ？
I don't see anything like that.
見えないわよ そんなの
Oh, a normal person shouldn't be able to see it at such a distance.
（阿良々木）
あ… 普通は この距離では
読めないか
Umm, the numbers "eight," "nine," and "shrine."
えっと 漢数字
十中八九の“八九”に“寺”で
The "eight" and "nine" plus "shrine" write out to be "eight nine tera."
はち きゅう てらって
並びなんだけれど
Well, that's pronounced "Hachikuji."
（戦場ヶ原）
まあ それは“はちくじ”ね
Hachikuji?
はちくじ？ じゃあ あれは
“はちくじ まよい”ってことか
So her name's Hachikuji Mayoi.
ふ〜ん
う〜ん こいつ どう考えても
子供が好きってタイプじゃないよな
She doesn't look like the type that likes small kids.
Hey, could you wait here for a second?
おい ちょっとここで
待っててくれるか？
Yes, but where are you going?
（戦場ヶ原）
いいけれど 阿良々木くん
どこかへ行くの？
I'm going to go talk to the elementary school student.
小学生に話しかけてくる
You shouldn't. You'll only get a scar on your heart.
やめておきなさい
傷つくだけよ
How can she say these spiteful things so nonchalantly...?
ホント ひどいことを
平気で言うよな こいつは
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
Yo. What's up?
よっ！ どうした？
Are you lost?
（阿良々木）道にでも迷ったのか
（八九寺(はちくじ)）あ…
フフツ
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
Please don't speak to me. I hate you.
話しかけないでください
あなたのことが嫌いです
What's wrong? Did something happen?
どうしたの？ 何かあったの？
I'm hurt. That's all that happened.
（阿良々木）
傷ついた　傷つくだけだった
I'm going to try again.
（阿良々木）もう１回 行ってくる
What exactly are you doing? Where are you going?
だから 何をしに どこへ行くのよ
Can't you tell with your eyes?
（阿良々木）
見りゃわかんだろうが！
Hey, you.
おい お前
You're lost, aren't you?
迷子なんだろ？
どこに行きたいんだ？
Where are you going?
Let me take a look at that memo.
そのメモ ちょっと貸してみろよ
Hey.
なあ
おい…
（八九寺）フン！
What's wrong? Did something happen?
どうしたの？ 何かあったの？
I was ignored by an elementary school girl.
（阿良々木）
無視された　小学生女子に
シカトされた
This time definitely... I'm going!
（阿良々木）
今度こそ… 行ってくる
I don't really know what you want to do or what you're doing...
阿良々木くんが何をしたいのか
何をしているのか
私には よく分からないのだけれど
（阿良々木）ほっとけ
Ignore me!
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Change
Center
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
A
Hikari
Credit
What do you think you're doing?!
何をするんですか！
So you finally turn around.
ようやく振り向いてくれたか
Anyone would turn around after such a beating from behind.
後ろから たたかれたら
誰でも振り向きます！
Well, it looked like you were having some difficulties.
いや お前 何か
困ってるみたいだったから
力になれるかなと思ってさ
So I was wondering if I could help you.
The kind of help a person who would suddenly attack an elementary school kid's head could offer...
いきなり小学生の頭を
たたくような人に
なってもらうような力なんて
この世界には ありません！
doesn't exist in this world!
Absolutely impossible!
全くもって皆無です！
A
Hikari
Credit
I'm sorry, okay?
いや だから 悪かったって
えっと
Um, my name is Araragi Koyomi.
僕の名前は
阿良々木暦(こよみ)っていうんだ
Koyomi?
Namashiro Park Management
暦ですか
女の子みたいな名前ですね
It sure sounds like a girl's name, doesn't it?
Namashiro Park Management
Girly, don't come near me.
女臭いです
近寄らないでください！
う…
で お前は何て名前なんだ？
So what's your name?
I'm Hachikuji Mayoi.
私は八九寺真宵(まよい)です
私は八九寺真宵といいます
I'm called Hachikuji Mayoi.
This is an important name given to me by my mom and dad.
お父さんとお母さんがくれた
大切な お名前です
In any case, stop talking to me.
とにかく
話しかけないでください！
I hate you.
私 あなたのことが嫌いです
Why?
（阿良々木）
なんでだよ？ 別に僕は
お前に危害を加えたりしないよ
I won't harm you.
There isn't a more harmless person than me in this town.
この町に住んでいる人間で
僕くらい人畜無害なヤツなんて
１人も いないんだぜ？
むうう… 分かりました
警戒のレベルは下げましょう
Very well, then. I'll be less alert with you.
That will make things easier.
そりゃ 助かるよ
Then, beastly man.
では 人畜さん
Beastly man?!
（阿良々木）
人畜さん？ 誰のことだ それは？
Who are you calling that?!
He's yelling at me! I'm so scared!
A
Name
どなられました　怖いです！
I'm sorry for yelling at you, but "beastly man" is going just a little too far.
いや〜 どなったのは
悪かったけれど
でも 人畜さんは ひどいって！
Anyone would have yelled.
誰でも どなるって！
Then, how should I address you?
では 何と お呼びしましょう
Well, a normal way of addressing me is good enough.
そりゃ 普通に呼べば いいよ
That is Araragi-san, right?
ならば“阿良々木さん”で
Yeah, normal is good. Normal is the best.
ああ 普通でいいな
普通 最高！
I hate you, Araragi-san.
私 阿良々木さんのことが嫌いです
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
Please leave immediately!
迅速に どっか
行っちゃってください！
No. As I was saying, you're lost, aren't you?
いや だから お前 迷子なんだろ？
A minuscule problem like this is hardly a problem for me.
この程度の事態 私は
全く平気です！
Don't be so stubborn.
意地 張ってんじゃねえよ
I am not.
（八九寺）意地なんて張ってません
（阿良々木）張ってるじゃん
You are.
Take this!
くらえ！
（阿良々木）ぐっ くく…
Namashiro Park Management
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（八九寺）あ〜 しまりました！
This is the end!
（阿良々木）イテッ
Ouch!
えい！
（八九寺）うくっ
（阿良々木）ハア
You're so stupid.
全くバカなヤツめ
Did you think that an elementary school student could beat a high school student?!
小学生が高校生に勝てるとでも
思ったか！
There was a figure of a man...
小学生女子を相手に
本気でケンカをして
who fought an elementary school kid, threw her over his back with all his might,
本気の一本背負いを決めた末に
and was boasting about his victory from the bottom of his heart, despite the fact that he was in high school.
本気で勝ち誇っている
男子高校生の姿が そこにはあった
Actually, that's me.
ていうか 僕だった
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Araragi-kun.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（戦場ヶ原）
阿良々木くん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
Please allow me to explain.
言い訳を させてください
Go ahead.
どうぞ
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
Well, let's just brush aside things of the past.
まあ 過去のことは とりあえず
置いておいてだな
She seems to have lost her way.
こいつ 道に迷ってるっぽいんだよ
I was thinking that I could help her.
何か 力になれるかなって思って
Hmm, really?
ふ〜ん そう
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
（阿良々木）うん？
No, I see.
いえ なるほど
事情は分かったわ
I understand the circumstances.
Ah, right, Senjougahara.
（阿良々木）
あっ そうだ 戦場ヶ原
If you heard the address of this area, you'd roughly know where it is, right?
Namashiro Park Management
お前 この辺の住所とか聞いたら
ある程度 分かるだろ？
Well yes, to a certain extent.
（戦場ヶ原）
そりゃまあ 人並みには
A
Change
Center
Hey, Hachikuji.
（阿良々木）おい 八九寺
Give this girl a look at that memo.
さっきのメモを このお姉ちゃんに
見せてみろ
It seems that I had a dream of being abused by an evil high school boy.
何だか凶悪な男子高校生に
虐待される夢を見ていました
Having that happen in real life sounds impossible.
逆夢ってやつかな
I see.
なるほど 逆夢ですか
Impossible, huh?
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
What's wrong? Take it.
何だよ 受け取れよ
I don't feel like touching you.
何だか あなたには
触りたくないわね
It's only touching the memo.
メモを受け取るだけだろうが
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Namashiro Park Management
I also don't wish to touch the things you've touched.
あなたが触った物にも
触りたくないわ
All right, I get it.
じゃあ 分かったよ
僕が読み上げりゃ いいんだろ
I will read it. Is that fine with you?
Eh...
え〜っと
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Namashiro Park Management
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Do you know where this place is?
どこだか分かるか？
I know that place.
ふむ そこなら分かるわ
That's good.
そりゃ 助かる
I don't know the exact location.
細かいところまでは
さすがに無理だけれど
But we should be able to find it based on our senses when we get there.
その辺りは たどりつけば
フィーリングで分かるでしょう
Namashiro Park Management
Then, let's go.
じゃ 行きましょうか
Namashiro Park Management
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
Let's go, Hachikuji.
行くぞ 八九寺
Namashiro Park Management
Oh, where are we going?
Namishiro Park Neighborhood Map
どこへですか？
Like I said, we are going to the location written on the memo.
だから このメモの住所
That girl knows the way. She will lead you there.
あの お姉ちゃんが分かるから
案内してくれるってさ
よかったな
Isn't that great?
Ah, she'll lead the way...?
はあ… 案内ですか
A
Change
Center
ん？ お前
迷子なんじゃないのか？
Are you not lost?
No, I'm lost.
（八九寺）いえ 迷子です
I'm the lost child of a snail.
かたつむりの迷子です
は？ かたつむり？
Snail
Snail?
No, I...
（八九寺）いえ 私…
It's nothing.
（八九寺）何でもありません
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part One
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part One
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part One
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part One
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part One
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part One
CONTINUED NEXT TIME
I'm Karen.
（火憐）火憐だぜ
（月火(つきひ)）月火だよ
I'm Tsukihi.
Even the kids of the kings are considered kings, right?
（火憐）
将棋の駒で王将ってあるじゃん
I've gotten that.
（月火）
あったあった ありましたよ
（火憐）
玉将って王将の偽物っぽいよな
Reading kings seem kind of fake, don't they?
（月火）ぽい
But the thing earlier seemed more like reading to me.
（火憐）
だけど 先にあったのは
玉将のほうなんだってさ
（月火）そうなの？
Oh really?
Because of corruption, they apparently become like kings.
（火憐）
誤植で王将になっちゃったらしいぜ
（月火）へえ〜
But every once in a while, aren't the kings a bit stronger?
（火憐）
でも 玉より王のほうが
強そうじゃねっつって
So nowadays reader kings are kind of in a heartbreaking state, huh?
今じゃ 玉将は下手の使う駒
（火憐）切ないよな
（月火）切ないね
A heartbreaking state, eh?
Quiz time.
（火憐）では 恒例の予告編クイズ
（月火）まだ３回目だけどね
It's that time, right?
Tsukihi-chan and I are twins, right?
（火憐）
私と月火ちゃんは双子ですが
（月火）双子じゃないよ！
（火憐）さて 十二星座のなかで
We're not twins!
Which of the 12 constellations is known as the twin constellation?
（火憐）双子の星座といえば？
（月火）双子座じゃん
Isn't it Gemini?
（火憐）
いや 魚座も実は双子なんだよ
No, actually, Pisces is also a twin constellation.
（月火）うん？
（火憐）双魚宮(そうぎょきゅう)！
It's true!
（月火）双魚宮！
It's true?
Next time, Mayoi Snail Part 2.
Next Time
Mayoi Snail, Part Two
（火憐･月火）
次回 まよいマイマイ 其(そ)の貮(に)
But it may not necessarily be a twin.
（火憐）
まあ 双子とは限らねえけどな
It could be like us.
（月火）私たちみたいにね